<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" >
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Letter from John Hunn to William Still, October 19, 1871</title>
        <author>
          <persName ref="#hunnjo">John Hunn</persName>
        </author>
        <respStmt>
          <resp> Transcription and encoding by </resp>
          <name xml:id="jd"> Jessica De Paola </name>
        </respStmt>
        <principal xml:id="fg">Francesca Giannetti</principal>
      </titleStmt>
      <extent>
      <measure unit="page" quantity="3">Three pages</measure>
      </extent>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Rutgers University Libraries</publisher>
        <availability>
          <ab>Public domain.</ab>
        </availability>
        <authority>Transcribed from digital files from the Historical Society of Pennsylvania</authority>
        <idno>hsp001</idno>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <msDesc>
          <msIdentifier>
            <repository>Historical Society of Pennsylvania</repository>
            <collection>Leon Gardiner collection of American Negro Historical Society records</collection>
            <idno>0008</idno>
          </msIdentifier>
        </msDesc>
        <bibl>Box 9G, Folder 11</bibl>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <p>Line breaks, paragraph breaks, and indentations have been preserved within the 
        transcription. The layout of the page has been preserved whenever possible. 
        Abbreviations and spellings have been maintained within the transcriptions, 
        and the full word and corrected or modern spellings have been provided. Images 
        of the original letters have been provided in order to show the original page 
        layout. Words or phrases that are deemed indecipherable have been noted as "unclear."
        </p>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
        </hyphenation>
      </editorialDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <correspDesc>
        <correspAction type="sent">
          <persName ref="#hunnjo">John Hunn</persName>
          <placeName>Beaufort, South Carolina</placeName>
          <date when="1871-10-19">October 19, 1871</date>
        </correspAction>
        <correspAction type="received">
          <persName ref="#stillwi">William Still</persName>
          <placeName>Philadelphia, Pennsylvania</placeName>
        </correspAction>
      </correspDesc>
      <textClass>
        <keywords scheme="#LCSH">
          <term>African Americans--Biography.</term>
          <term>Underground railroad.</term>
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change when="2025-05-06" who="#fg">first pass, minor edits, added project id and keyword</change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <standOff>
    <listPerson>
        <person xml:id="hunnjo" sex="1">
          <persName>
            <reg>John Hunn</reg>
            <forename>John</forename>
            <surname>Hunn</surname>
          </persName>
          <birth when="1818-06-25"><placeName>Kent County, Delaware</placeName></birth>
          <death when="1894-07-06"><placeName>Camden, Delaware</placeName></death>
          <occupation>Farmer, abolitionist, and engineer of the Underground Railroad in Delaware</occupation>
          <bibl><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/John_Hunn_(farmer)">Wikipedia</ref></bibl>
        </person>
        <person xml:id="stillwi" sex="1">
          <persName>
            <surname>Still</surname>
            <forename>William</forename>
          </persName>
          <birth notBefore="1821-10-07" notAfter="1821-11-17">
            <placeName>Burlington, New Jersey</placeName>
          </birth>
          <death when="1902-07-14">
            <placeName>Philadelphia, Pennsylvania</placeName>
          </death>
        </person>
    </listPerson>
  </standOff>
  <text>
    <body>
      <pb n="1" />
        <opener>
          <dateline>
            <placeName>Beaufort S.C.</placeName>
            <date when="1871-10-19">10<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> mo 19<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> 1871</date>
          </dateline>
          <salute><persName ref="stillwi"><choice><abbr>W<hi rend="superscript">m</hi></abbr><expan>William</expan></choice> Still</persName><lb/> Dear Friend</salute>
        </opener>
        <p>
          Thy letter<lb/> of 30<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> <hi rend="superscript"><choice><abbr>ulto</abbr><expan>ultimo</expan></choice></hi> <add place="above">was received;</add> asking for “such papers as you<lb/> might deem essential for the contemplated<lb/> sketch of your labors, sufferings &amp; sacrifices<lb/> in the cause of humanity”; also desiring<lb/> that such papers, together with an account<lb/> of my trial for assisting fugitive slaves;<lb/> might be forwarded at an early day.
        </p>
        <p>
	      I find myself unwilling to comply<lb/> with thy request.
        </p>
        <p>
	      Not from any false modesty<lb/> or desire to hide <del rend="strikethrough">any of my</del> the part taken<lb/> by myself in forwarding the cause of<lb/> Truth &amp; Human Freedom; but because<lb/> I have done nothing in the cause worthy<lb/> of public record.
        </p>
        <p>
	      All that I did was actually<lb/> necessary for my own comfort and peace of 
    <pb n="2"/>
          mind. Such being the case, I cannot see<lb/> the propriety of anything appearing from<lb/> my pen to enlighten the public.
        </p>
        <p>
	      When I made the remark in one<lb/> of my letters; <del rend="strikethrough">to thee</del> that some of my papers<lb/> might be serviceable to thee; I had no<lb/> reference to those concerning myself, but<lb/> to such as related to the fugitives with<lb/> whom I became acquainted, while in<lb/> the exercise of my position as engineer<lb/> on the Southern Line of the Underground<lb/>-Rail-Road.
        </p>
        <p>
	      There can be no<lb/> necessity for an account of my trial, as<lb/> my dear friend <persName>Thos. Garrett</persName> and myself<lb/> were tried at the same term of court<lb/> a history of his trial will be a history<lb/> of mine.
        </p>
        <p>
	      Nor can I give an account of<lb/> the trial and conviction of <persName>Samuel D<lb/> Burris</persName>, another dear friend mine; nor<lb/> of my connection therewith as it would<lb/> be a repetition of his account.
        </p>
    <pb n="3"/>
        <p>
	      Believing that I have “rendered a reason” for<lb/> not complying with thy request; I will further<lb/> state; that, I doubt the propriety of calling<lb/> those things “sufferings and sacrifices” which occur<lb/> to individuals who are engaged in any course of<lb/> action, which <add place="above" rend="carrot">(they believe)</add> is absolutely necessary for them<lb/> to pursue, in order to fulfill their duty towards<lb/> their fellow men.
        </p>
        <p>
	      My family and myself are well;<lb/> hoping that thyself and family are enjoying the<lb/> blessing of health.
        </p>
        <closer>
          <salute>I remain<lb/> very truly thy friend</salute>
          <signed><persName ref="hunnjo"><choice><abbr>Jno</abbr><expan>John</expan></choice> Hunn</persName></signed>
        </closer>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
