<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Garrison, W[illia]m Lloyd, letter, Roxbury, [Mass.], April 7, 1872, to William
          Still.</title>
        <author>
          <persName>Garrison, William Lloyd</persName>
        </author>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Transcription and encoding by</resp>
          <name xml:id="MH"> Michelle Hwang </name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Edited by</resp>
          <name xml:id="FG"> Francesca Giannetti </name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <extent>4 p.</extent>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Rutgers Community Repository (RUcore)</publisher>
        <availability>
          <ab>Reusable according to the Creative Commons License <ref
              target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/3.0/">Attribution Non-commercial
              Share-alike</ref>.</ab>
        </availability>
        <idno xml:id="DOI">doi:10.7282/T32R3PPP</idno>
        <idno xml:id="WMA">rutgers-lib:26931</idno>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Peter Still Papers, 1850-1875</title>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Rutgers Community Repository (RUcore)</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Rutgers University Libraries</pubPlace>
            <address>
              <addrLine>Alexander Library</addrLine>
              <addrLine>169 College Ave.</addrLine>
              <addrLine>New Brunswick, NJ 08901-1163</addrLine>
            </address>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
        <msDesc>
          <msIdentifier>
            <settlement>Special Collections and University Archives</settlement>
            <repository>Rutgers University Libraries</repository>
            <idno>MC 1392</idno>
          </msIdentifier>
          <msContents>
            <p>Correspondence (1850-1875), chiefly relating to Still's campaign to purchase his
              wife, Vina Still, and family held as slaves in Alabama and the publication (1856) of
              Kate E.R. Pickard's biography, The Kidnapped and the Ransomed; memo book (1853-1854)
              of funds collected; and Still family record (1798-1821). Persons and places
              represented include William Lloyd Garrison, Horace Greeley, Harriet Beecher Stowe, and
              Cortlandt Van Rensselaer, and Burlington, N.J., and Philadelphia, Pa. 57 items.</p>
          </msContents>
        </msDesc>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <p>Line breaks, paragraph breaks, and indentations have been preserved within the
          transcription. The layout of the page has been preserved whenever possible. Abbreviations
          and spellings have been maintained within the transcriptions, and the full word and
          corrected or modern spellings have been provided. Images of the original letters have been
          provided in order to show the original page layout and other markings that are not the
          author's. Words or phrases that are deemed indecipherable have been noted as "unclear." </p>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
        </hyphenation>
      </editorialDecl>
      <projectDesc>
        <p>Letters transcribed and encoded in partial fulfillment of an Aresty Research
          Assistantship, 2016-2017.</p>
      </projectDesc>
      <tagsDecl>
        <!-- Basic text formatting: bold, italic, underline, "normal," etc. -->
        <rendition xml:id="b" n="tiebp:bold" scheme="css"> font-weight:bold; </rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="i" n="tiebp:italic" scheme="css"> font-style:italic; </rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="u" n="tiebp:underline" scheme="css"> text-decoration:underline; </rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="n" n="teibp:normal" scheme="css"> font-weight:normal;
          text-decoration:none; font-style:normal; </rendition>
        <!-- Indentation -->
        <rendition xml:id="indent" n="tiebp:indent" scheme="css" scope="before"> text-indent:4em; /*
          The above method of describing an indentation for, say, a paragraph is preferred. The
          method being used is in response to a bug in some browsers whereby a block element, like a
          paragraph, is erroneously re-indented after interruption by another block element (like a
          list, which is valid, in TEI, inside a paragraph). */ content:"\A0\A0\A0\A0\A0\A0"; </rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent1" scheme="css"> display:block; padding-left:4em; text-indent:-2em; </rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent2" scheme="css"> display:block; padding-left:7em; text-indent:-2em; </rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent3" scheme="css"> display:block; padding-left:10em;
          text-indent:-2em; </rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="center" scheme="css"> display:block; text-align:center; margin-left:auto;
          margin-right:auto; text-align: center; </rendition>
      </tagsDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy xml:id="LCSH">
          <bibl>Library of Congress Subject Headings</bibl>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
      <listPrefixDef>
        <prefixDef ident="psn" matchPattern="([a-z]+_[a-z]+(_[a-z]+)*)"
          replacementPattern="still-personography.xml#$1">
          <p> In the context of this project, private URIs with the prefix "psn" point to
              <gi>person</gi> elements in the still-personography.xml file. </p>
        </prefixDef>
      </listPrefixDef>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <correspDesc>
        <correspAction type="sent">
          <persName>William Lloyd Garrison</persName>
          <placeName>Roxbury, Massachusetts</placeName>
          <date when="1872-04-07">April 7, 1872</date>
        </correspAction>
        <correspAction type="received">
          <persName>William Still</persName>
          <placeName cert="medium">Philadelphia, Pennsylvania</placeName>
          <date>Unknown</date>
        </correspAction>
      </correspDesc>
      <textClass>
        <keywords scheme="#LCSH">
          <term>Slavery--United States--History--19th century.</term>
          <term>African Americans--Biography.</term>
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change resp="#FG" when="2018-06-18">Removed teibp stylesheet declarations and added TEIP5
        schema and schematron. Edited transcription.</change>
      <change when="2018-09-09" who="#FG">Fixed divs. Edited correspDesc.</change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <pb n="1" facs="../images/26931_1.png"/>
      <div type="letter">
        <opener>
          <dateline>
            <placeName>Roxbury</placeName>, <date when="1872-04-07">April 7, 1872</date>. </dateline>
          <salute>Dear Mr. <persName ref="psn:william_still">Still</persName>:</salute>
        </opener>

        <p rendition="#indent"> I have already delayed too<lb/> long in thanking you for your
          presentation<lb/> to me of your voluminous<lb/> and well-executed work, “The<lb/>
          Underground Railroad.” I have<lb/> examined it with a deep and thrilling<lb/> interest. It
          is a most important<lb/> portion of Anti-Slavery History, which<lb/> but for your
          industry, research, and<lb/> personal experience and knowledge,<lb/> might nearly all have
          been<lb/> lost to posterity. Its reliableness,<lb/> moreover, cannot be called in
          question. <lb/> It is, therefore, not “fiction <unclear>founded</unclear><lb/> upon fact,”
          and embellished by a<lb/> lively imagination, but fact without<lb/> a particle of fiction,
            <del>and</del> narrated<lb/>
          <pb n="2" facs="../images/26931_2.png"/> in a simple, ingenuous, straightforward<lb/>
          manner, and needing no<lb/> coloring whatever. What a revelation<lb/> it makes of the
          barbarities of the<lb/> slave system - of the formidable obstacles<lb/> which interposed
          to prevent a<lb/> successful exodus from the house of<lb/> bondage - of the terrible
          exposures and<lb/> sufferings to which the fugitive slaves<lb/> were subjected in their
          attempts to be<lb/> free - of the daring and heroism required<lb/> to run the risk of
          betrayal, recapture,<lb/> starvation in the swamp and<lb/> drowning in the river,
          suffocation in<lb/> trunk or box, seizure by two-legged<lb/> and four-legged bloodhounds
          in<lb/> hot pursuit, and a thousand other<lb/> perils! How it illustrates, too,<lb/> the
          object subservience of the nation<lb/> to the Slave Power, so that even<lb/> in
            <placeName>Boston</placeName> the atrocious Fugitive<lb/>
          <pb n="3" facs="../images/26931_3.png"/> Slave Law was as effectually enforced<lb/> as it
          could have been in <placeName>New<lb/> Orleans</placeName>; and in all our broad
          domains<lb/> none <add place="above">could</add> give shelter or assistance<lb/> to the
          hunted and famishing<lb/> victim, except at the peril of <unclear>fire</unclear> and<lb/>
          imprisonment! And yet, numerous<lb/> as are the instances you have recorded,<lb/> they are
            <add place="above">only</add> samples of thousands<lb/> of others which can never be
          chronicled,<lb/> running through six generations.<lb/> May we trust our senses that<lb/>
          there is an end of all this wickedness -- <lb/> that a final and marvelous<lb/>
          deliverance has been wrought for<lb/> all in bondage? Yes, it is true: and<lb/> there has
          been the same divine interposition<lb/> as of old. “And the Lord said,<lb/> I have surely
          seen the affliction of<lb/> my people which are in Egypt, and<lb/> have heard their cry by
          reason of their<lb/>
          <pb n="4" facs="../images/26931_4.png"/> taskmasters; for I know their sorrows,<lb/> and I
          am come down to deliver<lb/> them out of the hand of the Egyptians.”<lb/> … “Thy right
          hand, O Lord,<lb/> is become glorious in power: thy<lb/> right hand, O Lord, hath dashed
          in<lb/> pieces the enemy!”<lb/>
        </p>

        <p rendition="#indent"> I hope that the sale of your<lb/> work will be widely extended,
          not<lb/> only that the large expense incurred<lb/> in its preparation and printing
          may<lb/> be liberally covered, but for the<lb/> enlightenment of the rising
          generations<lb/> to the inherent cruelty of the defunct<lb/> slave system, and to
          perpetuate<lb/> such an abhorrence of it as to<lb/> prevent all further injustice
          towards<lb/> the colored population of our land.<lb/> It is a book for every
          household.<lb/>
        </p>

        <closer>
          <salute>Yours, with best wishes,</salute>
          <signed><persName ref="psn:garrison">W<add place="above">m</add> Lloyd
            Garrison</persName>.</signed>
        </closer>

        <postscript>
          <ab>William Still.</ab>
        </postscript>

      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
