<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>May, Samuel J., letter, Syracuse, [N.Y.], February 28, 1861, to "Uncle Peter" [Peter
          Still]</title>
        <author>
          <persName>May, Samuel J.</persName>
        </author>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Transcription and encoding by</resp>
          <name xml:id="MH"> Michelle Hwang </name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Edited by</resp>
          <name xml:id="FG"> Francesca Giannetti </name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <extent>4 p.</extent>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Rutgers Community Repository (RUcore)</publisher>
        <availability>
          <ab>Reusable according to the Creative Commons License <ref
              target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/3.0/">Attribution Non-commercial
              Share-alike</ref>.</ab>
        </availability>
        <idno xml:id="DOI">doi:10.7282/T3KW5G58</idno>
        <idno xml:id="WMA">rutgers-lib:26923</idno>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Peter Still Papers, 1850-1875</title>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Rutgers Community Repository (RUcore)</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Rutgers University Libraries</pubPlace>
            <address>
              <addrLine>Alexander Library</addrLine>
              <addrLine>169 College Ave.</addrLine>
              <addrLine>New Brunswick, NJ 08901-1163</addrLine>
            </address>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
        <msDesc>
          <msIdentifier>
            <settlement>Special Collections and University Archives</settlement>
            <repository>Rutgers University Libraries</repository>
            <idno>MC 1392</idno>
          </msIdentifier>
          <msContents>
            <p>Correspondence (1850-1875), chiefly relating to Still's campaign to purchase his
              wife, Vina Still, and family held as slaves in Alabama and the publication (1856) of
              Kate E.R. Pickard's biography, The Kidnapped and the Ransomed; memo book (1853-1854)
              of funds collected; and Still family record (1798-1821). Persons and places
              represented include William Lloyd Garrison, Horace Greeley, Harriet Beecher Stowe, and
              Cortlandt Van Rensselaer, and Burlington, N.J., and Philadelphia, Pa. 57 items.</p>
          </msContents>
        </msDesc>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <p>Line breaks, paragraph breaks, and indentations have been preserved within the
          transcription. The layout of the page has been preserved whenever possible. Abbreviations
          and spellings have been maintained within the transcriptions, and the full word and
          corrected or modern spellings have been provided. Images of the original letters have been
          provided in order to show the original page layout and other markings that are not the
          author's. Words or phrases that are deemed indecipherable have been noted as "unclear." </p>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
        </hyphenation>
      </editorialDecl>
      <projectDesc>
        <p>Letters transcribed and encoded in partial fulfillment of an Aresty Research
          Assistantship, 2016-2017.</p>
      </projectDesc>
      <tagsDecl>
        <!-- Basic text formatting: bold, italic, underline, "normal," etc. -->
        <rendition xml:id="b" n="tiebp:bold" scheme="css"> font-weight:bold; </rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="i" n="tiebp:italic" scheme="css"> font-style:italic; </rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="u" n="tiebp:underline" scheme="css"> text-decoration:underline; </rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="n" n="teibp:normal" scheme="css"> font-weight:normal;
          text-decoration:none; font-style:normal; </rendition>
        <!-- Indentation -->
        <rendition xml:id="indent" n="tiebp:indent" scheme="css" scope="before"> text-indent:4em; /*
          The above method of describing an indentation for, say, a paragraph is preferred. The
          method being used is in response to a bug in some browsers whereby a block element, like a
          paragraph, is erroneously re-indented after interruption by another block element (like a
          list, which is valid, in TEI, inside a paragraph). */ content:"\A0\A0\A0\A0\A0\A0"; </rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent1" scheme="css"> display:block; padding-left:4em; text-indent:-2em; </rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent2" scheme="css"> display:block; padding-left:7em; text-indent:-2em; </rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent3" scheme="css"> display:block; padding-left:10em;
          text-indent:-2em; </rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="center" scheme="css"> display:block; text-align:center; margin-left:auto;
          margin-right:auto; text-align: center; </rendition>
      </tagsDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy xml:id="LCSH">
          <bibl>Library of Congress Subject Headings</bibl>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
      <listPrefixDef>
        <prefixDef ident="psn" matchPattern="([a-z]+_[a-z]+(_[a-z]+)*)"
          replacementPattern="still-personography.xml#$1">
          <p> In the context of this project, private URIs with the prefix "psn" point to
              <gi>person</gi> elements in the still-personography.xml file. </p>
        </prefixDef>
      </listPrefixDef>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <correspDesc>
        <correspAction type="sent">
          <persName>Samuel J. May</persName>
          <placeName>Syracuse, New York</placeName>
          <date when="1861-02-28">February 28, 1861</date>
        </correspAction>
        <correspAction type="received">
          <persName>Peter Still</persName>
          <placeName cert="medium">Burlington, New Jersey</placeName>
          <date>Unknown</date>
        </correspAction>
      </correspDesc>
      <textClass>
        <keywords scheme="#LCSH">
          <term>Slavery--United States--History--19th century.</term>
          <term>African Americans--Biography.</term>
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change when="2018-09-09" who="#FG">Proofread. Added a few persName tags.</change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <pb n="1" facs="../images/26923_1.png"/>
      <div type="letter">
        <opener>
          <dateline>
            <placeName>Syracuse</placeName>
            <date when="1861-02-28">Feb. <unclear>28</unclear>
              <lb/>1861.</date>
          </dateline>
          <salute>Dear Uncle <persName ref="psn:peter_still">Peter</persName>,</salute>
        </opener>

        <p rendition="#indent"> Since my return, I have inquired<lb/> carefully into the sale of the <choice>
            <reg>copyright</reg>
            <orig>copy right</orig>
          </choice><lb/> and stereotype plates of your book, and<lb/> believe I can now explain the
          matter, so as<lb/> to satisfy you, that no intended wrong<lb/> was done you, however
          unfortunate<lb/> for you the sale of those things may have<lb/> proved to you.<lb/>
        </p>

        <p rendition="#indent"> You understand, I presume, that the<lb/>
          <choice>
            <reg>copyright</reg>
            <orig>copy right</orig>
          </choice> and the stereotype plates belonged<lb/> at first to the publisher. When he
          failed<lb/> in business, and it became necessary that<lb/> those things should be sold,
          with the rest of<lb/> his effects, to somebody, -- I am told they<lb/> were offered first
          to you -- and offered<lb/> to you at a price much less than they<lb/> cost.
            Mr <persName>Hamilton</persName> assures me, they were<lb/> sold to Mr <persName
            ref="psn:joseph_parrish" cert="medium">Parish</persName> as your friend, and<lb/> that
          it was supposed you were to be<lb/> benefitted by the sale of them to him -<lb/> and would
          sooner or later become the<lb/> owner of them.<lb/>
        </p>

        <p rendition="#indent"> I hear that Mr Parish first offered<lb/> them to you for what they
          cost him, i.e. <lb/>
          <measure type="currency">$250</measure>.- and that when he found you<lb/>
          <pb n="2" facs="../images/26923_2.png"/> indisposed or unable to take them<lb/> off his
          hands - that he then offered<lb/> to let you have an edition of your<lb/> book printed
          from the plates, before<lb/> he should sell them to <choice>
            <reg>anybody</reg>
            <orig>any body</orig>
          </choice><lb/> else.<lb/>
        </p>

        <p rendition="#indent"> Now <add place="above">if</add> this statement is true, you<lb/>
          certainly have no reason to complain<lb/> of the publisher or of Mr Parish -- <lb/> though
          you might complain of your<lb/> hard fate in being unable to pay for<lb/> the <choice>
            <reg>copyright</reg>
            <orig>copy right</orig>
          </choice> and the plates.-<lb/>
        </p>

        <p rendition="#indent"> I wrote to Mrs <persName ref="psn:pickard_kate">Pickard</persName>
          from <placeName>Brooklyn</placeName>,<lb/> the day after I saw you, but<lb/> as I have not
          heard from her, I fear<lb/> she did not receive my letter. So<lb/> I wrote to her again
          yesterday, and<lb/> when I hear from her, if she gives<lb/> me any different account of
          the<lb/> matter, I will write to you again.<lb/> But, from all I can learn from<lb/>
          others, she has certainly done you no<lb/> wrong. You have no reason whatever<lb/> to
          blame her for the sale of the <choice>
            <orig>copy right</orig>
            <reg>copyright</reg>
          </choice>
          <lb/> and the plates, for it was<lb/> a loss to herself to have them sold<lb/> to <choice>
            <reg>anybody</reg>
            <orig>any body</orig>
          </choice> but yourself, or to some <lb/> friend of yours for your benefit.<lb/>
          <pb n="3" facs="../images/26923_3.png"/> I have heard that after consulting you<lb/> Mr
          Parish did sell the <choice>
            <reg>copyright</reg>
            <orig>copy right</orig>
          </choice> and<lb/> the stereotype plates of your book to a<lb/> Mr
            <persName>Jones</persName> of <placeName>London</placeName>. But even there<lb/> they
          are not beyond your reach.<lb/> Printing is done, I believe, more cheaply<lb/> in London
          than in <placeName>New York</placeName>, so<lb/> that, whenever you are ready to<lb/> buy
          them, I presume you can have<lb/> an edition of three or five hundred<lb/> copies printed
          for you in London<lb/> and delivered to you in <placeName>Burlington</placeName><lb/> for
          about the same price you<lb/> would have to pay for them, if<lb/> they should be printed
          for you in<lb/> New York. If you wish, I will<lb/> write to Mr Jones and as certain
          how<lb/> much he will charge you for them.<lb/>
        </p>

        <p rendition="#indent"> But, Uncle Peter, I am quite as much<lb/> worried about your
          difficulty with<lb/> Mr <persName ref="psn:dillwyn_smith">Smith</persName> respecting the
          price of your<lb/> house and land. I hope it will soon<lb/> be settled and without a
          lawsuit.<lb/> Suppose you and Mr Smith agree<lb/> upon three good men, to whom you<lb/>
          will refer the whole matter, and<lb/> let them decide how the difficulty<lb/> shall be
          settled.<lb/>
        </p>

        <pb n="4" facs="../images/26923_4.png"/>

        <p> Let those three men come together<lb/> at some convenient time and place<lb/> then let
          Mr Smith state the facts of<lb/> the case as he believes to be true, <lb/> then you make
          your statement of<lb/> the facts as you understand them, <lb/> and each of you bring
          forward<lb/> whatever witnesses or other evidence<lb/> you may have to suppose your<lb/>
          several statements and let the<lb/> three referees decide between you.<lb/> Then whatever
          may be their decision,<lb/> do you and Mr Smith abide by<lb/> it. This is the best way to
          settle.- <lb/> I hope soon to hear you have done<lb/> so.- Give my very kind regards<lb/>
          to your <persName ref="psn:vina_still">wife</persName> and son, and<lb/> believe me<lb/>
        </p>

        <closer>
          <salute>Truly your friend</salute>
          <signed><persName ref="psn:samuel_may">Samuel J. May</persName>.</signed>
        </closer>

        <postscript>
          <p> P.S. Last Friday, I rode out to<lb/> Onondaga Academy to see <persName
              ref="psn:catharine_still">Catherine</persName>.<lb/> She seemed to be in very good
            health,<lb/> and was glad to hear from home.<lb/> She is not satisfied with her
            situation, <lb/> thinks she does not receive as<lb/> much instruction as she ought to.-
            <lb/> I think she will not stay there long.- <lb/>
          </p>
        </postscript>

      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
